Guide to the Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter papers
1839-1951
YCAL MSS 483
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
83
(85 boxes)
The Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter Papers consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, financial papers, and other material that document the work and lives of the writers Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter. The Papers provide evidence of Stewart and Winter's writing careers as well as political activism. The Papers also relate to Stewart and Winter's friends and family, including Lincoln Steffens. The Papers illuminate the creative lives of Stewart and Winter and offer insights into artistic production, literary circles, and the interconnection of artistry and activism in the twentieth century.
Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1894-1980
Winter, Ella, 1898-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Donald Ogden Stewart, Donald Ogden Stewart Junior and Peter Steffens, 1970-1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Donald Ogden Stewart (1894-1980)
Donald Ogden Stewart, American playwright, humorist, screenwriter, and political activist, was born in Columbus, Ohio on November 30, 1894 to Gilbert Holland and Clara Landon Ogden Stewart. Stewart attended Philip Exeter Academy (1909-1912) and Yale University (1912-1916), where he was a member of Skull and Bones and served as the assignments editor for the Yale Daily News. Following graduation Stewart worked for American Telephone and Telegraph and enlisted in the Navy during World War I. In 1919, while once again working for American Telephone and Telegraph, Stewart was transferred to Minneapolis where he met F. Scott Fitzgerald who was at that time living in St. Paul.
In 1920 Stewart devoted himself to becoming an author and moved to New York where he reconnected with Fitzgerald. Fitzgerald introduced Stewart to Edmund Wilson, and by extension, members of the Round Table, a group of writers who met at the Algonquin Hotel (most famously including Dorothy Parker and Robert Benchley). Like many of the "Round Table" authors, Stewart wrote for Vanity Fair as well as Smart Set, Bookman, and Harper's Bazaar. Stewart's first book, A Parody Outline of History (1921), is a collection of his pieces from the Bookman.
In 1922 Stewart traveled to Europe with his mother, first visiting Paris and then going to Vienna and Budapest. Stewart began work on Aunt Polly's Story of Mankind (1923) in Europe and completed the book while at the MacDowell Colony in New Hampshire. Stewart continued to visit Europe in the 1920s where his circle of friends included Philip and Ellen Barry, F. Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, Ernest Hemingway, John Dos Passos, Archibald MacLeish, Gerald and Sara Murphy, and Gilbert Seldes. This circle of friends inspired Stewart, who wrote Mr. and Mrs. Haddock Abroad (1924) with their encouragement, over a month-long period.
While in Paris in 1925 Stewart met Beatrice Ames, and the two married on July 24, 1926 in Montecito, California. The couple honeymooned in Europe, which Stewart subsidized by writing for the Chicago Tribune, and then moved to the U.S. where they lived in Hollywood and then New York City. During this period Stewart wrote for the New Yorker and became involved in acting. Stewart appeared in Philip Barry's play Holiday and performed in the movie Not So Dumb. These experiences compelled Stewart to write and act in his first play Rebound (1930).
In 1932 Stewart moved to Hollywood with his family (which now included sons Ames Ogden and Donald Ogden, Junior) in order to pursue a career as a screenwriter. Stewart had already written scripts for Laughter (1930) and Tarnished Lady (1931). With the exception of his original screenplays Tarnished Lady (1931) and Night of Nights (1939), Stewart's work as a screenwriter largely involved adapting plays or working with a team of other writers. Stewart was nominated for an Academy Award for best screenplay for Laughter (1930-31) and won best screenplay for his adaptation of Philip Barry's play The Philadelphia Story (1940).
Stewart served as president of the Hollywood Anti-Nazi League, president of the League of American Writers, and a member of the board of the Screen Writer's Guild. Stewart met his second wife, author Ella Winter, at a political rally and the two were married on March 4, 1939 (Stewart and Beatrice Ames had divorced in 1938). Stewart and Winter lived at Frazzle Top Farm (New York), New York City, and California. While living at Frazzle Top Farm Stewart focused on writing plays, but was pulled back to Hollywood to work on Keepers of the Flame (1942). In 1950 Stewart was blacklisted for his political activities and in 1951 he and Winter moved to London. While Stewart's career as a screenwriter was effectively curtailed he continued to write plays, including The Kidders (1957), and wrote screenplays, such as Escapade (1955), using his father's name (Gilbert Holland) as a pseudonym. Stewart's last book was his autobiography By a Stroke of Luck! (1975).
Stewart died on August 2, 1980 of complications following a heart attack.
Ella Winter (1898-1980)
Writer, lecturer, and political activist Ella Winter was born Eleonora Sophie Wertheimer on March 17, 1898 in Melbourne, Australia, to Adolph and Freda Lust Wertheimer. The family moved to England in 1910 so that Winter and her siblings Rosa and Rudolph could receive a European education. German-born, Ella Winter's parents converted from Judaism to Lutheranism and around 1910 changed the family name from Wertheimer to Winter.
Winter graduated from the University of London with Honours in Modern Languages (1914) and from the London School of Economics, B. Sc. (Econ), with First Class Honours in Public Administration (1919). While a student Winter worked as a research assistant and secretary for Professor Felix Frankfurter, a position that involved her in the Paris Peace Conference in 1918. Winter returned to London where she finished her studies, taught at the London School of Economics, worked for the Committee on Nationalization, and was an assistant to Henry F. Grady. Between 1920 and 1923 Winter was a member of the Foreign Affairs Committee of Parliamentary Labor Party and managed H.G. Wells' campaign for Parliament. The Institute of Industrial Research awarded Winter a research fellowship at Cambridge University's Psychology Laboratory. During this period Winter also translated Diary and Letters of Otto Braun (1924) and Mentality of Apes by Wolfgang Köhler (1926) from German into English.
While in Paris in 1918 Winter had met and fallen in love with American journalist Lincoln Steffens, who was thirty-two years her senior. The couple reunited in 1923 and moved to France and then Italy. While living on the continent their circle of acquaintances included Jo and Yvonne Davidson, Ernest Hemingway, Louise and Billy Bullitt, Charles Erskine Scott Wood and Sara Bard Field. Winter, who was six months pregnant, and Steffens married in Paris to avoid social stigma in the U.S. (reacting against what Steffens considered restraining social convention they later divorced but continued to live happily together). Their son Pete Stanley was born in San Remo, Italy in 1924.
In 1927 Winter and Steffens moved to the U.S. and settled in Carmel, California (Winter became a naturalized American citizen in 1929). While living in Carmel Winter and Steffens befriended a number of artists, journalists, and political figures, including Robinson and Una Jeffers, John Steinbeck, Marie de L. Welch, and Samuel Darcy.
Having already written articles for the Manchester Guardian, Winter pursued a career in journalism, first editing The Carmelite (1928-1930), and then The Pacific Weekly (1934-1936), and Your World (1946), and contributing articles to Argosy, Collier's, Hollywood Tribune, Ladies' Home Journal, Liberty, London Daily News, The Nation, New Republic, New York Times, Scribner's Magazine, and U.S. Week.
Winter also worked as a foreign correspondent. She made several trips to the Soviet Union, first in 1930-1931, which resulted in her book Red Virtue (1933), and then during World War II, at which time Winter was a correspondent for the New York Post, an experience that led to her book I Saw the Russian People (1945).
As a journalist Winter visited post-war Germany, Austria, Czechoslovakia, and Yugoslavia (where she interviewed Tito for Alliance ) in 1947. In 1958, with the Chinese National Women's Federation as hosts, Winter visited China for two months with the intention of writing another book.
Politically astute and engaged, Winter often addressed social injustice in her writings, for example, in Red Virtue she considers the status of women in Russia, and in other articles she argued for the rights of migrant workers in California.
Following the death of Lincoln Steffens, Winter published a number of books celebrating his life and work, including Lincoln Steffens Speaking (1936), Letters of Lincoln Steffens (1938), and The World of Lincoln Steffens (1962).
Winter married Donald Ogden Stewart on March 4, 1939 and the two lived in California, Frazzle Top Farm in upstate New York, New York City, and London, where they settled in Hampstead. Winter published her autobiography, And Not to Yield, in 1963.
She died on August 5, 1980, two days following Donald Ogden Stewart's death.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter Papers consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, financial papers, and other material that document the work and lives of the writers Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter. The Papers provide evidence of Stewart and Winter's writing careers as well as political activism. The Papers also relate to Stewart and Winter's friends and family, including Lincoln Steffens. The Papers illuminate the creative lives of Stewart and Winter and offer insights into artistic production, literary circles, and the interconnection of artistry and activism in the twentieth century.
Stewart's work as a humorist, playwright, and screenwriter is documented in his correspondence, drafts, and printed versions of his writings, which trace his creative process as well as the production of his work on stage and in film. For example Stewart's play The Kidders is traced from a typescript draft to photographs of its production at the Arts Theatre Club and various reviews. Letters between Stewart and directors, such as Leo Mittler and Samuel Wanamaker, in addition to letters filed under the title of publications and productions in the Correspondence series, also provide a window into Stewart's writing career.
Ella Winter's writing process is evident in the various research files, drafts, and printed material in the Papers. Winter's work as a journalist and editor are captured in the printed versions of a number of newspapers, including The Carmelite and The Pacific Weekly, both of which Winter edited. Winter's travels for book projects in Russia and China are traced in her research files, drafts of articles, and correspondence. For example, the Writings series includes a file containing notes, drafts, photographs, and correspondence relating to Winter's travels in China and an abandoned book project. While there are few documents pertaining to Winter's translation work, there is some correspondence between Winter and Havelock Ellis, who provided the introduction to her translation of Diary and Letters of Otto Braun.
The Papers document Donald Ogden Stewart and Ella Winter's political activism. Several documents reflect Stewart's commitment to liberal causes; for example his correspondence and a file on "Hollywood Anti-Nazi League" relate to his role as president of the association. Ella Winter's political advocacy is documented in various drafts, printed versions, and correspondence. Winter's files on "Labor Strikes" and "Migratory Labor Camp reports" in addition to her correspondence with Carol Decker and John Steinbeck relate to her work on behalf of migrant workers.
The Papers also record Stewart and Winter's persecution as a result of their political activities, and in particular, their communist sympathies and affiliations. For example, Winter's correspondence file "Reds" pertains to an FBI investigation of Winter and Lincoln Steffens during which an investigator, Charles Baczsy, posed as a neighbor and friend. The Papers also reflect Stewart's ordeal of being blacklisted from Hollywood. For example the Writings series contains drafts and reviews for Escapade, a Hollywood production for which Stewart was forced to write under a pseudonym. Stewart also reflects about being blacklisted in his autobiography By a Stroke of Luck! (drafts and related material for which are also located in the Writings series).
Stewart and Winter's circle of friends included a number of prominent writers, artists, directors, and actors, as their correspondence and personal papers illustrate. For example, the Correspondence Series includes letters reflecting Stewart's connection with the Algonquin Round Table (various letters relate to Dorothy Parker); American expatriates in 1920s France (correspondents include Ernest Hemingway, Gerald and Sara Murphy, and others); and Hollywood in the 1930s and 1940s (correspondents include Samuel Wanamaker). Winter and Lincoln Steffen's circle also included a number of friends involved in arts and politics. As her correspondence indicates, Winter maintained friendships with sculptor Jo Davidson and his wife Yvonne, authors Charles Erskine Scott Wood and Sara Bard Field, poet Robinson Jeffers and his wife Una, and poet Marie de L. Welch. Photographs in the Personal Papers series also capture these relationships. Combined these documents reflect the culturally rich communities in which Stewart and Winter were immersed.
Stewart and Winter's personal lives, including their education, marriage, previous relationships, and family life, are also documented in the Papers. For example, the Correspondence Series includes letters between Stewart and Beatrice Ames and between Winter and Lincoln Steffens as well as between Stewart, Winter, and their children, parents, and siblings. The Personal Papers and Financial Papers series are also a window into Stewart and Winter's early lives, including, Donald Ogden Stewart's education at Yale University and Ella Winter's education at the London School of Economics. Diaries, day planners, and other documents provide a glimpse into their daily lives, and a number of photographs offer a sense of Stewart and Winter's milieu.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1854-1980. II. Writings, 1915-1975. III. Personal Papers, 1881-1976. IV. Financial Papers, 1909-1972.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Algonquin Round Table; Blacklisting of authors -- United States; Foreign correspondents -- United States; Journalists -- United States; Motion picture industry -- United States; Political activists -- United States; Screenwriters -- United States; Social justice -- United States; Carmel (Calif.) -- Newspapers; China -- Description and travel; Europe -- Description and travel; Russia -- Description and travel; Photographs; Authors; Foreign correspondents; Journalists; Screenwriters; Darcy, Samuel, 1905-; Davidson, Jo, 1883-1952; Davidson, Yvonne, -1934; Field, Sara Bard, 1882-1974; Fitzgerald, F. Scott (Francis Scott), 1896-1940; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; Jeffers, Robinson, 1887-1962; Steffens, Lincoln, 1866-1936; Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1894-1980; Welch, Marie de L. (Marie de Laveaga), 1905-1974; Wells, H. G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946; Winter, Ella, 1898-1980; Wood, Charles Erskine Scott, 1852-1944; Harcourt Brace & Company
- Correspondence, 1854-1980; Series I; 15.0 linear feet (15 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Donald Ogden Stewart Correspondence and Ella Winter Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Donald Ogden Stewart's correspondence with authors, publishers, literary agents, production companies, film directors, and actors reflects his work as a writer. Stewart's work as a screenwriter is represented in his correspondence with the production company Ealing Studios, directors Leo Mittler and Samuel Wanamaker, and actors Marshall H. Williams and Katherine Hepburn. Stewart associated with a number of different circles of authors, and these connections are also recorded in his correspondence, for example, letters regarding Dorothy Parker relate to his inclusion in the Algonquin Round Table and his correspondence with Ernest Hemingway reflects one of many friendships with American expatriates in France in the 1920s. Stewart's friendship with F. Scott Fitzgerald is represented in their correspondence and in Stewart's correspondence, in later life, with literary scholar Matthew Bruccoli. Stewart corresponded with author Louis Untermeyer, who like Stewart, was blacklisted in the 1950s under the presumption of communist sympathies. The series also contains correspondence relating to specific writings.
  Stewart's correspondence also reflects his personal life. The series includes correspondence between Stewart and his first wife Beatrice Ames Stewart (who married Ilya A. Tolstoy following their divorce) and their sons Ames Ogden Stewart and Donald Ogden Stewart, Junior. Stewart's relationships with his second wife Ella Winter, and her son Peter Steffens, are also represented in their correspondence. Stewart's parents, Gilbert Holland and Clara Ogden Stewart, and extended family are also included in the series, and provide insight into Stewart's close relationship with his mother in particular. Unsorted correspondence includes letters between Stewart and a number of other friends and authors.
  Ella Winter's correspondence reflects her work as an author and political activist. The series includes Winter's correspondence with publishers, such as Harcourt, Brace and Company and Little, Brown and Company, magazines, and editors, including Joseph Freeman, which provide evidence of Winter's work as a journalist and editor. Winter's circle of friends included a number of artists and writers, as the correspondence attests, and the series contains letters with Jo and Yvonne Davidson, Charles Erskine Scott Wood and Sara Bard Field, Robinson and Una Jeffers, John Steinbeck, and Marie de L. Welch.
  Documentation of Winter's early political involvement can be found in her correspondence with Professor Felix Frankfurter and H.G. Wells. The series also reflects Winter's involvement in advocating against social injustice, as her correspondence with Samuel Darcy and union organizer Caroline Decker demonstrate.
  The series also relates to Winter's personal life, and includes her correspondence with family members and extended relatives. Winter's correspondence with Lincoln Steffens and their son Pete Steffens provides insight into their relationships; for example, Steffens and some of Winter's loved ones from this period address her in their correspondence as "Peter," a nickname she received from Steffens who named her after the forever youthful and idealistic Peter Pan. Winter's correspondence with her sisters-in-law Dot Hollister and Laura Suggett are also included in the series. Letters between Winter and Donald Ogden Stewart, Ames Ogden Stewart, and Donald Ogden Stewart, Junior illuminate her second marriage and later years. The series also includes correspondence between Winter and her parents (Adolph and Freda Lust Winter), siblings (Rudolph and Rosa Winter), and cousin Fredric Wertham who was a noted psychiatrist and author.
  - Donald Ogden Stewart Correspondence
    - "A" general, 1951-1975 (Box 1)
    - "A"-"B" general, 1912-1930 (Box 1)
    - "A"-"Z" general, 1915-1945, undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
      Includes folder "Mr. & Mrs. Stewart 1945"
    - American Film Institute, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Arts Theatre, 1952-1958 (Box 1)
    - "B" general, 1956-1980, undated (Box 1)
    - Barton, A. H., 1958-1975 (Box 1)
    - Becker, Charles A., 1947 (Box 1)
    - Bender, George H., TLS to "Dear Brother", undated (Box 1)
    - Best, Marshall A. [re: Dorothy Parker], 1970 (Box 1)
    - Board of Supervisors, Hall of Records, Los Angeles from Donald Ogden Stewart, 1936 (Box 1)
    - Bontemps, Arna, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Boudin, Cohn, & Glickstein, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - Brandt & Brandt Dramatic Department, Inc., 1951 (Box 1)
    - Brewster, Kingman, 1972 January 21 (Box 1)
    - Briggs, George A., TLS to Mrs. Peter, 1927 May 6 (Box 1)
    - Brown, Geoffrey, 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - Bryan, Joseph, III, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Brucolli, Matthew, 1970-1979; 3 (Box 1)
    - "Bucky", 1947 (Box 1)
    - "C" general (Box 1)
    - "C"-"D" general, 1910-1921 (Box 1)
    - Cameron, Angus and Sheila, undated (Box 1)
    - Carr, Virginia Spencer, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd., 1951 (Box 1)
    - "D" general, 1956-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Day, Clarence, Jr., ALS to Farrar, undated (Box 1)
    - Donaldson, Scott, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Dos Passos, John, 1925 (Box 1)
    - Dunham, Barrows and Alice, 1969-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - "E" general, 1956-1975, undated (Box 1)
    - "E"-"G" general, 1912-1941 (Box 1)
    - Ealing Studios, 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - "F" general, 1949-1976 (Box 1)
    - Fay, Terry to Ella Winter, 1948 (Box 1)
    - Fischer Verlag, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Fitzgerald, F. Scott, 1920, undated (Box 1)
    - Fowler, George S., TL to "Ed" Wilson about Stewart's A Parody Outline of History, undated (Box 1)
    - Frankley, Lawrence, R., 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Fritchman, Frances Putnam, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - "G" general (Box 1)
    - Gager, John, 1912-1915, undated (Box 1)
    - Glynn?, Martin, ALS to George H. Doran Co., 1922 February 18 (Box 1)
    - Gray, Anne, 1975, undated (Box 1)
    - "H" general (Box 1)
    - "H"-"J" general, 1910-1933 (Box 1)
    - Hayduk, Marie-France [contains dramatization of Mr. and Mrs. Haddock Abroad ], 1980 (Box 1)
    - Hellman, Lillian [re: Dorothy Parker], 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Hemingway, Ernest, 1924-1931, undated (Box 1)
    - Hepburn, Katherine, 1942, 1956 February 9; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Higgins, Grover, TLS to Mrs. Charles C. Higgins about Donald Ogden Stewart, 1918 September 4 (Box 1)
    - Hollywood Anti-Nazi League, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Hollywood Committee for Writers in Exile, 1940 (Box 1)
    - Hope Leresche & Steele, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - "I" general, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
    - "J" general, 1957-1976 (Box 1)
    - James, Fred, TLS (draft) Yale students, 1915 May 7 (Box 1)
    - "K" general, 1957-1979 (Box 1)
    - "K"-"M" general, 1912-1940 (Box 1)
    - Keats, John [re: Dorothy Parker], 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Kent, Rockwell, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Kindler, Don [re: Dorothy Parker], 1969 December 30 (Box 1)
    - "L" general, 1951-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Lipmann, Heinz, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - Lambert, Paul, 1976
    - "M" general, 1942-1977 (Box 2)
    - M.A. Jacobs & Sons, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
    - Mayfield, Sara, 1969-1970, undated (Box 2)
    - MCA Artists, Ltd., 1956-1958 (Box 2)
    - Mittler, Leo, 1943-1946 (Box 2)
    - Murphy, Gerald, 1925 (Box 2)
    - "N" general, 1966-1977 (Box 2)
    - "N"-"P" general, 1912-1925, undated (Box 2)
    - The Nation, 1954 September 27 (Box 2)
    - New Statesman [re: profile on Charlie Chaplin, enclosed], 1957 (Box 2)
    - New York Central Railroad to Shepard and Donald Ogden Stewart, 1915 September 27-29 (Box 2)
    - Nowell, Elizabeth [re: Thomas Wolfe's title and meeting of League of American Writers], 1954 December 5, 1958; 2 (Box 2)
    - "O" general, 1956-1978, undated (Box 2)
    - Stewart, Gilbert Holland and Clara Ogden, ALS from Mrs. John Ogden, undated (Box 2)
    - Olivier, Lawrence, 1957 November 29 (Box 2)
    - Oppenheimer, George, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Outhwaite, Anne Stewart to M. Shippey, 1932 June 1 (Box 2)